physicsworld.com 2019-06-23

# Privacy and cookies - IOP Publishing

## Who we are

IOP Publishing Limited **(“IOPP” or “we” or “us” or “our”)** publishes a range of journals, ebooks, magazines, conference proceedings and websites for the scientific community (the “content”).

To support the publication of the content, we may gather and process your personal information.  We will do this in accordance with this Privacy Notice **(“notice”)** and in compliance with the relevant data-protection regulations and laws. This notice provides you with information regarding your rights and our obligations and explains how, why and when we process your personal information.  References in this notice, to “website” or “websites” are to the specific IOPP website that links to this notice.

IOPP’s registered office is at Temple Circus, Temple Way, Bristol BS1 6HG and we are a registered company in England and Wales under company number 00467514 **.  **We are registered on the Information Commissioner’s Office Register, registration number Z6045891, and act as the data controller **.**

This notice was last updated on 23 May 2018.

## Your privacy

We are committed to ensuring the security and protection of the personal information we process. We will make every reasonable effort to protect your privacy by adopting a high level of website security and adhering to company policies on how we store and use personal information.

This notice relates to our use of the personal information we collect from you, or that you provide to us, via the online services we make available to you, by phone, e-mail, in letters and other correspondence, and in person.  It has been created to help you understand our views and practices regarding your personal information.

We recommend that you read this notice prior to using our websites, product and services.  If we change this notice we will post the changes on this page and may place notices on other pages of the website so that you will be aware of the personal information we collect and how we will use it.  If you use this website or our products and services, or access our content on this website, after any such change has been made, you will be deemed to have read and accepted the change.

## Personal information we may collect from you

The personal information we collect about you, or that you provide to us, will be dependent on your relationship with us, the services we provide to you, the way in which you choose to interact with us and your level of engagement with us.

### Personal information you give us

You may give us personal information when you fill in forms on our websites or when you correspond with us by phone, e-mail, in writing or otherwise.  The types of personal information we may collect about you include but are not limited to:

  * your name and contact information, including your e-mail address;
  * your institutional affiliation and level of education;
  * your employer or the organisation that you represent;
  * demographic information such as your research interests;
  * payment information; and
  * opinions or other information you provide when you complete surveys, enter competitions or respond to questions from us.

### Personal information we collect about you

When you visit our websites, we may collect the following information automatically:

  * technical information, including the Internet Protocol (IP) address used to connect your computer to the internet, your login information, your geographic location, browser type and version, browser plug-in types and versions, operating system and platform; and
  * information about your visit, including the source of your visit, the full click path, mouse movement through our websites (including date and time); services you viewed, searches made on our websites, page response times, download errors and length of visits to certain pages.

### Personal information we collect at receipt and opening of e-mails

When you open an e-mail sent by us, we may collect the following personal information automatically:

  * technical information, including; your geographic location, browser type and version, device type, operating system and platform; and
  * information about your e-mail consumption, including the full click path from within and on to our sites (including date and time), whether the e-mail was delivered, shared, unsubscribed from, opened, deleted or forwarded.

Personal information from third parties

From time to time, and as permitted by applicable law(s), we may collect personal information about you from other third-party sources, including publicly available data sources and your employer or university/school.  This personal information may be used to update and enhance any existing personal information that we currently hold.

How we use your personal information

Depending on your relationship with us, we may process your personal information in the following ways:

  * to provide our products and services to you or to facilitate the provision of products, services and content to your employer, university or institution;

  * to respond to your requests and enquiries;
  * to invite you to participate in research studies, to submit work for our content or to attend live events or webinars;
  * to invite you to peer review and to manage the peer-review process;
  * to publish your name, institution, country, ORCID ID, and in some cases your e-mail address alongside your work;
  * in the course of arranging a press release;
  * administering and managing our relationships with individuals who sit on our editorial Advisory Boards;
  * to process payments from you (including, but not limited to, article publication charges, subscriptions or payments for any products or services that you choose to purchase from us);
  * to process payments to you (including, but not limited to, refunds or reimbursements, or payments to you for services provided to us);
  * to request your participation in surveys, focus groups, or other initiatives which help us to gather personal information used to develop and enhance our products and services, for example, to measure the effectiveness of our peer review process, we may analyse and measure user behaviour and performance, trends, demographics and interests;
  * from time to time to share the results of surveys, focus groups or other similar initiatives with our publishing partners but, in this case, we will not include information which will allow you to be identified;
  * to keep you updated about our products and services, latest content, industry news, events and webinars, where you have opted-in to such communications.  Where you have told us about your research interests, we may use this, together with the information we gather about the use of our products and services, to help you get the most out of our products and services;
  * to provide access to restricted parts of our websites;
  * to produce statistics about the usage levels of our websites to allow us to understand what we are doing well and where we can improve the online services we offer, as well as other internal purposes, such as website and system administration or internal audits and reviews.  We may share aggregated statistics to third parties that we work with, but these statistics will not include information which will allow you to be identified; and
  * to comply with applicable law(s) (for example, to comply with a court order) or to carry out professional ethics/conduct investigations.

We will process your personal information for the purposes identified above on the following bases:

  1. our legitimate interests, which include, but are not limited to, processing your personal information for the purposes of providing and enhancing the provision of our products, services and information or to invite you to submit work for our content;
  2. where processing is necessary to perform our contract with you or to take steps before entering into a contract with you;
  3. as necessary to comply with our legal obligations, resolve disputes and enforce our contractual agreements; and
  4. where you have consented to our use of your personal information for a specified purpose. Where this is the case, you have the right to withdraw your consent at any time.

Our use of your personal information for marketing activities

**Marketing by post:** occasionally, we will send you marketing information by post where we have decided that it is beneficial to you as a customer and in our interests.  Such information will be non-intrusive and is processed on the grounds of legitimate interests.

**Marketing by e-mail:** where you have consented to us sending you e-mail updates about our content including, but not limited to, our online content, industry news and updates, events and webinars, competitions and surveys, you are free to withdraw this consent at any time.  If you have provided information about your interest areas, or have purchased or used our products and/or services, we may use this information to tailor the content of our emails to you.  We will not send you marketing emails if you have opted out of receiving them.  Any marketing emails we send you will include an unsubscribe link at the end of the e-mail. ** **

If you would like to stop receiving marketing emails from us, you can let us know by:

  * clicking the “unsubscribe” link in any promotional e-mails you receive from us;
  * e-mailing us at [customerservices@iop.org](mailto:customerservices@iop.org) (please ensure you tell us if you would like to opt out from all e-mail marketing communications or just a particular update; and/or
  * phoning us on 0117 929 7481 (Mon–Fri 9am–5pm BST/GMT).

Our e-mails may contain a “web beacon pixel” to tell us whether they have been opened and to verify any clicks through to links or advertisements within the e-mail.

We may use this information for purposes including determining how to improve our communications to users, which of our e-mails are more interesting to users and to query whether users who do not open our e-mails wish to continue receiving them.

The pixel will be deleted when you delete the e-mail.  If you do not wish the pixel to be downloaded to your device, you can read the e-mail in plain text view or with images disabled.

## Surveys and contests

From time-to-time this website may request information from users via surveys or contests. Participation is completely voluntary and the user therefore has a choice whether or not to disclose any information requested.

Information requested may include contact information (such as name and delivery address) and demographic information.  Contact information will be used to notify the winners and award prizes. Survey information will be used for the purposes of monitoring or improving the functionality of this website.

How long we will retain your personal information

We may retain certain records for other legitimate reasons (including after your relationship with us has ended), for example to maintain records of articles published in our content, to resolve any potential disputes and to comply with reporting and retention obligations.

Who we share your personal information with

We will never sell, trade or rent your personal information to others.   However, we may share your personal information with selected third parties. We require that our third-party service providers only use your personal information as necessary to provide the requested services.  It is likely that the identity and categories of the third-party service providers with whom we share your personal information will change during the life of your relationship with us.  Depending on that relationship, and your use of our websites, it is anticipated that your personal information will be disclosed to the following categories of third-party service providers who perform functions on our behalf.  As examples:

  * for the provision on article indexing services;
  * for the production of MARC records;
  * author information processed for the creation, management and preservation of archived articles;
  * to allow academics to track, verify and showcase their peer review and editorial contributions across the world’s academic journals;
  * to streamline the manuscript submission process, improve the management of author and reviewer databases and improve the accuracy of name-based article repository searches;
  * hosting providers for the secure storage and transmission of your personal information;
  * database software providers for the management and tracking of your personal information;
  * identity management providers for authentication purposes;
  * e-mail sending services who send communications on our behalf regarding our products and services;
  * payment solution providers for the secure processing of payments you provide to us;
  * technology providers who assist in the development and management of our web properties;
  * fulfilment and postal vendors for the fulfilment of our products and services;
  * survey and research providers who perform studies on our behalf;
  * our Editorial Board members who perform various functions on our behalf;
  * other companies within the IOPP Group, who may perform outreach on our behalf regarding our products and services; and
  * legal and compliance consultants, such as external counsel, external auditors, or tax consultants.

## Links and third parties

This website may contain links to third-party websites and services.  Please be aware that IOPP is not responsible for the privacy practices of any third parties.  We encourage our users to read the privacy statements of these third-party websites and services.  This notice applies solely to information collected by this website.

Where we store your personal information

By providing us with your personal information, you acknowledge that it may be transferred to, stored at and processed at a destination inside or outside the European Economic Area by us, our affiliates and/or other third parties.  Please do not submit any personal information to us if you do not wish for it to be transferred internationally.

## Your rights

Under certain circumstances, by law you have the following rights in respect of the personal information we hold about you. For more information about these rights or if you wish to exercise them please contact us.

**Request access to your personal information** (commonly known as a “subject access request”). This enables you to receive a copy of the personal information we hold about you. You will be asked to provide the following details:

  * the personal information you want to access;
  * the nature of your relationship with IOP, for example if you are an author, a subscriber etc; and
  * the date range of the information you wish to access.

We may also need you to provide information that will help us confirm your identity. If we hold personal information about you, we will give you a copy of the information in an understandable format together with an explanation of why we hold and use it.

Once we have all the information necessary to respond to your request we’ll provide your information to you within one month.  This timeframe may be extended by up to two months if your request is particularly complex.  In this case, we will notify you and keep you updated.

**Request correction of the personal information** that we hold about you. If the personal information we hold about you is inaccurate, or your personal information changes (such as your email address), IOPP will correct, update or remove that your personal information as appropriate, where we are notified by you.  This can usually be done by you within any personalisation options of this website (where applicable), or by contacting us.

**Request erasure of your personal information.** This enables you to ask us to delete or remove personal information where there is no good reason for us continuing to process it. Please note that whilst we will honour your request wherever possible, we may need to retain some personal information about you for example, where we are required to retain records to comply with our legal obligations.

**Object to processing of your personal information** where we are relying on a legitimate interest (or those of a third party) and there is something about your particular situation which makes you want to object to processing on this ground. You also have the right to object to use of your personal information for marketing purposes, as described in the “Our use of your personal information for Marketing activities” section of this notice.

**Request the restriction of processing of your personal information.** This enables you to ask us to suspend the processing of personal information about you, for example if you want us to establish its accuracy or the reason for processing it.

**Request the transfer of your personal information** to another party. Whenever IOPP processes your personal information, by automated means based on your consent or based on an agreement, you have the right to get a copy of your data transferred to you or to another party. This only includes the personal data you have submitted to us.

**What to do if you’re not happy  
**In the first instance, please talk to us directly so we can resolve any problem or query. You also have the right to contact the Information Commissions Office (ICO) if you have any questions about Data Protection. You can contact them using their helpline 0303 123 113 or at [www.ico.org.uk](http://www.ico.org.uk/).

### How to contact us

If you wish to talk through anything in our privacy policy, find out more about your rights or wish to exercise them, please contact our Customer Services Team who will be happy to help.

  * By post: Customer Services, IOP Publishing Ltd, Temple Circus, Temple Way, BS1 6HG
  * By telephone: +44 (0)117 929 7481
  * By e-mail: [custserv@iop.org](mailto:custserv@iop.org)

### Cookies

**What are cookies?**  
This website may place small text files, called cookies, on your computer to distinguish you from other users of this website.  These cookies monitor how you use this website so that IOPP can make improvements, and are also used to give you the best user experience (for example by remembering your login details so that you do not have to enter them each time).  Some cookies may also be placed by third parties, for example Facebook and Google, if you use their services via this website, to monitor how you use their services and to target relevant advertising to you when you visit other websites on which they advertise.

In most cases, cookies do not contain personally identifiable information

### What cookies may be placed?

This website may use the following types of cookies:

  * Strictly necessary cookies (Type 1): these cookies are essential in order to enable you to move around this website and use its features, such as accessing secure areas of this website.  Without these cookies, certain services you have asked for cannot be provided.
  * Analytical/performance cookies (Type 2): these cookies allow IOPP to recognise and count the number of visits to this website and to see how visitors move around this website when they are using it, so that we can improve how this website works.  These cookies do not collect personally identifiable information.
  * Functionality cookies (Type 3): these cookies remember choices you make to improve your experience on this website; for example, your user name, language or region.
  * Targeting cookies (Type 4): these cookies are placed by third parties to collect information about your browsing habits when you elect to use their services, in order to make advertising relevant to you and your interests.

You can find out more information about the individual cookies actually used on this website by viewing the [IOPP Cookie Directory](http://ioppublishing.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/IOPCookiesDirectoryBristolSites.xlsx).

IOPP is not responsible for the use of cookies by third parties, and users are encouraged to read the privacy statements of those third-party service providers before using their services.

### How do I opt-out of cookies?

Most web browsers allow some control of most cookies through the browser settings.  To find out more about cookies, including how to see what cookies have been set and how to manage and delete them, visit [www.allaboutcookies.org](http://www.allaboutcookies.org/).  You should note that deleting certain cookies may prevent you from accessing certain parts of this website and/or may affect your user experience.

To opt out of being tracked by Google Analytics across all websites, and not just this website, visit: [tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout](http://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout)
